A Guide to the Pauline E. Burks Family Paper, 1763-1985
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Pauline E. Burks Family Papers, 1763-1985
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Broaddus family (Amherst County, Va.); Edmonds family (Amherst County, Va.); Burks family (Amherst County, Va.); Burks, Pauline E.; Vaughan family (Amherst County, Va.); Taliaferro family (Amherst County, Va.)
Ms1992-037
9 Cubic Feet 15 boxes; 4 oversize folders
Pauline E. Burks of Richmond, Virginia, collected genealogy materials about her husband Broaddus Vaughan Burks' family. The papers include correspondence, account books, essays, receipts, newspapers, and plats and surveys of the Broaddus, Burks, Edmonds, Taliaferro, and Vaughan families of Amherst County, Virginia. Materials focus mainly on the Vaughan and Burks families and range from 1760s land grants to 1970s family correspondence.
19 containers; 9.0 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by its creator and her daughter in 1989, 1992, 1993 and 1994.
Biographical Information
Pauline Englehard Burks, a Richmond, Virginia resident, researched the genealogy of her husband's (Broaddus Vaughan Burks) family. In doing so, she amassed correspondence, account books, receipts, newspapers, and other documents about the Broaddus, Burks, Edmonds, Taliaferro, and Vaughan families of Amherst County, Virginia. In 1995 she published the book Roots, Shoots and Runners: Taliaferro, Broaddus, Burks, Vaughan and Allied Families As Seen in Their Letters, Bible Records and Family Papers.
Alexander Hairston Burks married Ellen T. Broaddus. In 1879, their second child, Franklin "F.T." Taliaferro Burks (1849-1921), would marry his second wife, Hortense Washington Vaughan (1867-1955), the youngest of the four children of Dr. Washington "Wash" L. Vaughan and Francis "Fannie" Shields. Her siblings included noted doctor and surgeon Dr. George Tully Vaughan; Eugene Neville Vaughan; and Matilda Corinne Vaughan Hoffman. F.T. and Hortense Burks had 4 children: Pearl Burks Rossner Burnley Miles; Frank T. Burks, Jr.; Garnett M. Burks, who married architect Lorenzo Simmons Winslow; and Broaddus Vaughan Burks. Broaddus Burks (1898-1985) married Pauline Genevieve Englehard (b. 1909) in 1931, and they had two children.
Scope and Content
The P.E. Burks Family Papers include correspondence, account books, essays, receipts, newspaper clippings, family Bibles, and plats and surveys of the Broaddus, Burks, Edmonds, Taliaferro, and Vaughan families of Amherst County, Virginia.
Papers about the families include 18th-century land and property information for Virginia and 19th-century financial papers and ledgers as well as both personal and business correspondence. Most early materials pertain to the Broaddus, Edmonds and Taliaferro families. More contemporary materials from the late 19th and 20th centuries are found in the Vaughan and Burks papers. Most of the 20th-century papers are the informal correspondence of the Broaddus and Pauline Burks family, dating from the 1930s to the 1980s.
Other materials include a set of transcriptions of record books from Amherst County, Virginia from a series called Courthouse Miniatures, and other printed materials, such as magazines and newspapers. The magazine and newspaper selection consists only of selected issues and clippings from the periodicals, but contains interesting local news and advertisements. Also of note are a few clothing catalogs, patterns, and sewing instructions from around 1900. Children's publications such as Youth's Companion and activity pages complement the Virgnia schoolteacher information found in the Burks and Vaughan family materials.
Arrangement
The Burks papers are arranged into two sections. Series I contains family papers divided by family name. Series II contains general historical and genealogical materials divided by type of material.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Women -- History
Contents List
- FAMILY PAPERS
  - BROADDUS FAMILY
    - Broaddus and Taliaferro family plats and deeds, 1837-1866, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Plat of land in Amherst County, 1837
      - Plat of land sold by James F. Taliaferro to John F. Taliaferro, 1859
      - Plat of survey for A. Taliaferro's heirs, Amherst County, 1866
      - Plat of land near Tear-Jacket Mountain, n.d.
      - Deed from Richard P. Smith to Dudley Sandidge, n.d.
    - John W. and E.E. Broaddus - Receipts, accounts, bills of lading, and other financial papers, 1832-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to John W. and Bettie E. Broaddus, 1838-1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Printed materials (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Copied form letter from American Bible Union requesting funds, 1857
      - Article on Andrew Broaddus in Religious Herald, Jan 13, 1921
      - Article on Andrew Broaddus in Religious Herald, Feb 14, 1924
      - Program from Sesqui-Centennial Celebration of Mount Moriah Baptist Church, Amherst Co., Virginia, 1934
      - Amherst County Historical and Natural Beauty Tour guide, 1974
      - Register of General Assembly of Virginia listing [John] Broaddus, 1867-1868 Convention (photocopy), n.d.
  - EDMONDS FAMILY
    - Plats and surveys, c.1786-1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Deed from John Mays and wife to James Edmonds in Amherst Co., 1789
      - Menos Wright survey, Amherst Co., 1793
      - Samuel Edmonds survey by James Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1796
      - James Edmonds survey by James Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1796
      - James Edmonds survey by James Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1800
      - Samuel Edmonds survey by Joseph Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1805
      - Indenture between Samuel Edmonds and Rowland Edmonds in Nelson Co., 1809
      - Plat of land conveyed from Sarah Edmonds to George Vaughan, Nelson Co., 1839
      - Three Edmonds plats in Amherst Co.
  - TALIAFERRO FAMILY
    - Land grants, plats and land indentures, 1763-1839 (Folder 1)
      - Land grant, King George III to Charles Taliaferro, Albemarle Co., 1763
      - Indenture between Samuel Marksberry and Charles Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1765
      - Land grant, King George III to Hugh McKeebs, Amherst Co., 1769
      - Indenture between Lunsford Lomax, Jr. to Charles Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1770
      - Land grant, King George III to Joseph Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1772
      - Land grant, Gov. Edmund Randolph, Esq., to William Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1788
      - Land grant, Gov. Henry Lee, Esq., to Joseph Higginbotham, Amherst Co., 1793
      - Indenture between Samuel Edmonds and wife, Alice Edmonds, to Roland Edmonds, Amherst Co., 1796
      - Land grant, Gov. Thomas W. Randolph, Esq., to Benjamin Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1820
      - Land grant, Gov. Thomas W. Randolph, Esq., to Benjamin Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1822
      - Plat for Rowland Edmunds by John Hill, Nelson Co., 1836
      - Plat for William Edmunds by John Hill, Nelson Co., 1836
      - Plat for Capt. George Vaughan by John Hill, Nelson Co., 1839
    - Transcriptions of oversize land grants, 1763-1822 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Land indentures and plats, 1795-1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Indenture between Zacharias Taliaferro and wife Sally and Benjamin Taliaferro, 1795
      - Plat for Benjamin Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1802
      - Indenture between William Clarke and Benjamin Taliaferro, Amherst Co., 1817
      - Plat of land divided between Frances T. Burks and Bettie W. Burks, Amherst Co., 1873
      - Plat for Leonard H. Childress and Richeson Henley, Amherst County, n.d.
    - Correspondence and legal papers, 1837-1868 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes letters to Childress, Snead, Broaddus, and Taliaferro families
    - Marriage proposal from Z. Drummond to Belinda Caroline Taliaferro, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Taliaferro family illustrated Bible, includes birth, death and marriage records, n.d. (Box 11)
  - BURKS FAMILY
    - Family bills, receipts, plats, 1873-1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters between Hortense W. Vaughan and F.T. Burks, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hortense Vaughan Burks and Rose Berryman Burks - Teacher contracts and educational materials, 1886-1906 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sewing booklets and patterns of Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1885 - c.1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Frank T. Burks, 1890-1912 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters to Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1896-1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Deeds for Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1899, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1899-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Information on cows owned by Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1900-1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Printed materials, c.1900-1915, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes: Consumer Sugar Pledge from Sears, Roebuck and Co.; Blank application to Ku Klux Klan; Fabric samples from John Wanamaker and Edward Ridley and Sons; Bank brochure with information about Panama Canal; Obituary of F.T. Burks; Refund checks from Montgomery Ward; Newspaper clippings
    - Membership in Tobacco Grower's Cooperative Association, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Twenty-two assorted issues of the magazine The Mayflower Log which becomes The Washingtonian, 1926-1929 (Box 7)
      These issues all have drawings by Garnett Burks in them.
    - Pauline Englehard Burks Music History Scrapbook, c.1927 (Box 4)
    - West Virginia University Memory Book and general scrapbook compiled by Pauline Englehard Burks, c.1927-1989 (Box 8)
      Includes: Pittsburgh University and West Virginia University materials ca. 1928, newspaper clippings, buttons, admission tickets, programs, dance cards, wedding announcements, grades. Family letters, baby shower booklet for Pauline, wedding announcements and obituaries, greeting cards, church programs, ca.1930-1989
    - Letters from Neville Rosser to Pearl Burks Miles, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Genealogy notes by Pauline Burks (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Genealogy and correspondence of Vaughan, Burks and Clayton families, c.1900-1960 (Box 12, Folder 1a)
    - Burks family correspondence, greeting cards, receipts, 1911-1947 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Includes letters from friend who's a missionary in Japan in the 1940s
    - Letters to Hortense Burks, 1905-1913 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Pauline Englehart's high school diploma, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - West Virginia University lab book with notes by Pauline Englehart, 1928 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Pauline Englehart Burks, 1937-1954 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Broaddus and Pauline Burks and Hortense Burks, 1935-1952 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Broaddus and Pauline Burks, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Hortense Burks' will, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Letters to Virginia Department of Highways regarding the widening of Route 29 in Amherst Co., 1955-1959 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Letters to Broaddus and Pauline Burks, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Burks family letters, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence and greeting cards to and from the Broaddus and Pauline Burks family, 1960-1967 (Box 13, Folder 1-12)
    - Correspondence and greeting cards to and from the Broaddus and Pauline Burks family, 1968-1978 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence and greeting cards to and from the Broaddus and Pauline Burks family, 1979-1985 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Training course diploma from Sunday School Board, 1922 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Scholarship program participation certificate for Liberty Baptist College, 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Friends of Liberty certificate, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Burks family and friends namecards, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Typescript copy of Letitia Preston Floyd's 1843 Memoirs [original in Draper Manuscripts at Wisconsin Historical Society] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Burks family Bible, includes birth, death and marriage records, n.d. (Box 6)
  - VAUGHAN FAMILY
    - Deeds, receipts, etc. of George Vaughan, Jr., 1797-1860 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes list of Rowland Edmonds' slaves, 1836
    - Mitchell's School Atlas with notes, poems, diary entries, recipes, 1849-1865 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Two account books of Washington L. Vaughan, c.1850-1875 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Washington L. Vaughan - Bills, receipts, 1853-1869 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Washington L. Vaughan - Bills, receipts, notary public information, 1870-1889 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence to Washington L. Vaughan, 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - School essays by George Tully Vaughan, 1870-1878 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bills and correspondence to Fannie E. Vaughan, 1870-1900 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters from E. Neville Vaughan to mother and sister, 1878-1898 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters from George Tully Vaughan to sister, Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1887-1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters to George Tully Vaughan, 1878-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Includes some letters from E. Taliaferro, program for recognition program at Georgetown in 1929, and newspaper clipping about 88th birthday
    - Newspapers and newspaper clippings and issues with columns about Dr. George Tully Vaughan,, 1897-1929 (Folder 2)
      Includes Amherst Progress, The News [Lynchburg, VA], The Washington Post, and the Washington Times
    - School essays by Hortense W. Vaughan, letters to HWV and HWV's teacher contracts, c.1880-1888 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbooks and diaries compiled by Hortense W. Vaughan (Burks)
      - Three diaries written while in Farmville, VA, Feb. 1885 - Feb. 1887 (Box 4)
      - School notebook with notes, essays, and doodles, c.1886 (Box 4)
      - Black 1860s account ledger later used as scrapbook with newspaper clippings and colored advertising cards (Box 4)
      - Marbled-cover 1868 account ledger of D.S. Woodson later used as scrapbook with newspaper clippings, colored advertising cards, and cyanotype photographs of a house, young girls, and teenage girls (Box 4)
      - Green 1877 George Tully Vaughan exercise notebook for Latin and German later used as scrapbook for newspaper clippings, mostly about making handicrafts and some medical advice and remedies (Box 4)
      - Tan scrapbook with newspaper clippings of poetry, advice, stories and pictures, and colored advertising and name cards, 1880 (Box 4)
      - Green scrapbook with newspaper clippings of poetry, advice, stories, and obituaries, including some about Broaddus and Vaughan families, c.1905 (Box 5)
      - Red scrapbook with newspaper clippings and colored advertising cards (Box 5)
      - Tan scrapbook with newspaper clippings of poetry, advice, stories and pictures, and colored advertising and name cards (Box 5)
    - Letters and teacher contract of Corinne Vaughan, 1882-1897 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Hortense W. Vaughan about her marriage to F.T. Burks, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters from George Tully Vaughan to mother, Fannie E. Vaughan, 1894-1896 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letters and clippings concerning Vaughan family, 1870-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes: Newspaper clippings about G.T. Vaughan and wife; Poetry written on printed advertisements; Correspondence; Invitation to Christmas Soiree at Virginia Female Institute; Printed advertisement for Bank of South-Western Missouri - W.L. Vaughan & Co.
    - Letter to editor about Poindexter's Raid by Judge H.C. Shields, Hortense W. Vaughan's grandfather, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Three unidentified account and memo books, possibly of Hortense Vaughan Burks, 1890-1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- GENERAL GENEALOGICAL AND HISTORIC PAPERS
  - COPIES OF TRANSCRIPTIONS, AMHERST COUNTY, VIRGINIA - COURTHOUSE MINIATURES, COMPILED BY BAILEY FULTON DAVIS
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book A, 1761-1765, compiled, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - An Abstract of All A Items in Wills from 1761-1919 and A Marriages from 1801-1854, compiled, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Will Books, 1761-1919, for the B Section, Indices for Testators, Legatees, Administrators, Bondsmen, and All Family Names, compiled, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book B, 1761-1961, Cross-indexed as to Grantors and Grantees, compiled, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book C with Cross-Index, compiled, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book D, compiled, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book E, compiled, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - An Abstract of All Items in Deed Book F, Grantors Arranged in Sequence and Grantees Indexed, compiled, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Impressed Property Claims found in Order Books and Some interesting Data Found in an Order Book, compiled, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - PUBLICATIONS AND EPHEMERA
    - Housekeeping in Old Virginia (published volume with handwritten notes and pasted clippings), 1884 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Loose inserts from Housekeeping in Old Virginia, 1890-1919, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ca. 30 assorted issues of The Cheerful Letter, 1897-1924 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Printed religious, medical, and advertising materials, 1834-1912 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes: Catechisms of the Wesleyan Methodists; Our Home Above booklet; Abide with Me booklet; Our Story Quarterly, Vol. III, No. 1, 1906; Primary Quarterly, Vol. 23, No. 2, 1906; Colored chromolithograph ephemera; Advertisements for medicines; Prof. Jesse Beery information on training horses
    - Magazines and catalogs, 1880-1898 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Home Dressmaking booklet, 1898
      - Peterson's Magazine, April 1880
      - The Delineator, April 1892
      - H. O'Neill and Company's Catalog, Fall and Winter 1893-1894
      - The Leisure Hour Library, No. 9, Dec. 1895
    - Clothing and pattern catalogs for women and children, 1908-1925 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - National Cloak and Suit Company, New York, 1908
      - Bellas Hess and Company, New York, New York, Fall and Winter 1908-1909
      - The Mabley and Carew Company, Cincinnati, Ohio, Spring and Summer 1909
      - The Progressive Farmer Book of Fashions, Spring and Summer 1925
    - Four pages pulled from issues of Farm and Home, 1907-1908 (Box 9)
    - One copy of newsprint magazine Comfort, Sept. 1909 (Box 9)
    - Five pages pulled from various newsprint publications, 1905-1932 (Box 9)
    - Four newspaper clippings about execution of Clarence Richeson, 1912 (Box 9)
    - One copy of newsprint magazine The Farmer's Wife, Jan. 1914 (Box 9)
    - Issues and excerpts from "Youth's Companion", 1888-1895 (Box 9)
    - Issues and excerpts from "Youth's Companion", 1896-1911 (Box 10)
    - Advertising section for quit-smoking remedy, Who Will Free the Tobacco Slave?, 1914 (Folder 3)
    - Program for movie, The Wanderer, 1925 (Box 7)
    - Sixteen newspaper clippings about White House renovation and its architect, Lorenzo S. Winslow, 1934-1987 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1959-1975 (Box 9)
    - Broadside advertisement for lecture and lawn party by Dr. A. Bolling, eye doctor, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - NEWSPAPERS
    - Lynchburg Daily News, Aug 10, 1869 (Folder 3)
    - Richmond Christian Advocate (incomplete), October 11, 1894 (Folder 3)
    - Religious Herald [Richmond, VA], October 1, 1896 and December 21, 1899 (Folder 3)
    - The Amherst New Era (three incomplete issues), 1901 and 1907 (Folder 3)
    - The Orphanage News [Baptist Orphanage, Salem, VA], February 1908 (Folder 3)
    - The Amherst Progress, June 11, 1908 and June 23, 1910 (Folder 3)
    - The News [Lynchburg, VA] (incomplete), October 15, 1913 and Dec. 5, 1917 (Folder 3)
    - News series, The Kaiser as I Knew Him for Fourteen Years, by Arthur N. Davis, in The Amherst Progress (incomplete issues), Sept. to Nov. 1918 (Folder 3)
    - The News [Lynchburg, VA] (incomplete), October 11 and 20, 1922 (Folder 4)
    - Amherst New Era-Progress, Bicentennial Edition, October 12, 1961 (Folder 4)
    - The Morgantown Post and The Dominion-News, "Festival Time" section, Sept. 25, 1963 (Folder 4)
    - Amherst New Era-Progress, Bicentennial Edition, July 1, 1976 (Folder 4)
    - The News [Lynchburg, VA], Bicentennial Edition, July 4, 1976 (Folder 4)